European banks just told the ECB they
are tightening lending standards by the
most since 2023.
At the same time, they said an increase
in demand for loans is coming from a
corporate sector that is facing
increasing liquidity pressures that have
them on edge. This is why despite the
fact that everybody knows the ECB is
going to hike rates, probably not
tomorrow, more likely in June, European
banks anyway are buying a boatload of
government bonds. In fact, it was the
most in any 3-month period behind just
March of 2020 and the first quarter of
last year. If you remember the first
quarter of last year and the mess that
was. But notice the differences.
Back then, in those two cases, interest
rates, policy rates anyway, were going
down. And that's not all. The Europeans
offered up even more grim economic
statistics for their economy, starting
with sentiment tanking and especially in
services. Yes, it's even more evidence
that the service side of the economy is
going to be bearing the brunt of the
shock where sentiment among providers
there in Europe, it fell to the lowest
level in 5 years, going all the way back
to the bad days in early 2021. So, you
can see where European banks are coming
from on lending. They'd already told the
central bank 3 months ago that their
loan officers were exhibiting a \quote}
high degree of risk aversion. That's the
term the ECB report itself used. So,
this follow-up shows they are indeed
acting on those concerns by tightening
up lending standards. As I mentioned
before, we need to keep a close eye on
Europe because it will tell us whether
the energy shock is being contained and
if not, just where it will likely be
going. Now, Asia, we know that's getting
hit directly by the lack of oil flow,
but then the spillover go from there if
they continue to spill over in terms of
prices, but also other kinds of economic
decay, which we're already seeing in all
these different ways across Europe.
There are also more, let's call call
interesting parts of the bank lending
surveys as well as the bank data itself,
which I'll I'll go over here. And all of
this just in time for the ECB's meeting
tomorrow. And while I don't expect them
to raise rates, do expect them to start
sounding increasingly hawkish to set up
for a potential June rate hike. Because
let's face it, outside of everything
that's going on in the banking sector
and the real economy,
central bankers over there are very much
intent on repeating the mistakes that
Jean-Claude Trichet made back in 2011
twice, as well as 2008, so that makes it
not a repeat or even a three-peat, more
likely a four-peat. But listen to what
the banks are doing, not necessarily the
central banks.
But then again, we have other central
banks like those in North America who
are actually sounding more rational and
reasonable. So before we step into
Europe's problems, it's worth noting
what the Bank of Canada said earlier
today. It's again, it's been weird how
reasonable and rational the Canadians
are being about oil prices. They're not
ready to chase the inflation narrative
by any means, even as petroleum and
energy costs continue to soar. This is
the very thing that has all the hawks
all over the world salivating at the
prospects of hiking rates. It's exactly
what lured Jean-Claude Trichet into what
really should be central bank infamy.
They see oil as inflation or at the very
least a huge inflation risk. So oil goes
up big time and rate hike fever gets
really hot. And let's not forget,
officials in Ottawa at the start of this
year, they said and they indicated that
maybe their next move in 2026 was going
to be a rate hike anyway. They were
already leaning in that direction, so
for the Bank of Canada to come out and
say, "Hey, our rates are pretty good
here. We need to look past the
short-term oil price spike and what
that's going to do to the CPI this month
and probably the next couple."
That's just a reasonable and rational
reaction, rather than the overreaction
that we're going to get from the Casey
Jeffs of the world. So the Bank of
Canada's statement itself noted, quote,
"As expected, so far there is little
evidence that oil prices have fed
through more broadly to goods and
services prices, but this warrants close
attention in the months ahead." They're
going to say that. They're always going
to say that. "Near-term inflation
expectations have moved up with higher
gasoline prices and still elevated food
price inflation, but longer-term
inflation expectations have remained
anchored." But the real factor which is
holding down the inflation rate hiking
itch in Canada as well as the Federal
Reserve is the next part. Quote, "The
labor market is soft." I love how they
say soft. It's worse than soft. "With
subdued employment growth over the past
year." Really no employment growth, just
like in the United States. "And job
losses in sectors targeted by US
tariffs. The unemployment rate remains
in the 6.5 to 7% range and only because
Canadian workers are dropping out of the
labor force, just like their American
counterparts, reflecting both" This is
their statement again. "Weak hiring and
fewer job seekers." And the fewer job
seekers are from labor force dropouts.
In other words, despite all the happy
talk about the economy holding up,
officials know they're in a bad spot to
begin with even before we get to the
energy shock. And that's not nothing. As
I've said, a very fragile economy with a
weak labor market doesn't need nearly as
much of an oil price nudge to get to the
edge of the economic cliff, if not go
right over it. Before we go on with our
video today, let me ask you a question.
What if your gold could actually pay you
every single month in more gold? That's
what today's video sponsor, Monetary
Metals, lets you do.
And here's how it works. You still own
the gold. It's still in your name. It's
fully insured. But instead of just
sitting there doing nothing, it actually
it starts working for you. Monetary
Metals has built a system that turns
idle gold into productive gold, earning
real yield paid in physical gold, not
dollars. No selling, no trading, no
converting. You keep your gold and every
month you get more of it. It's a simple
idea, but it solves a big problem. If
gold is money, it should act like money
and now it finally can.
If you're a long-term gold holder
looking for a smarter way to store
value, check them out at
monetary-metals.com/snyder.
Again, that's
I highly recommend booking a call with
them today to see if they're the right
fit for you. We thank Monetary Metals
for their sponsorship, but now let's get
back to the rest of our video.
That's really the theme for this video.
Even if European Central Bankers can't
see it right now, European Bankers are
behaving in a way that is keeping
Canadian Central Bankers rational and
reasonable. This is in many ways is very
simple. It's very simple and basic
economics. Oil shocks historically do
not lead to inflation. They produce
price changes in the short run, but
inevitably what happens is what the Bank
of Canada implied in its statement. A
soft labor market gets to be a lot
softer rather than prices shoot up and
then keep shooting up and keep shooting
up into some kind of inflationary
spiral. And like I said, European banks
don't just know it, they're acting on it
in a couple of different ways.
So, it really is that simple starting
with a historic case for energy shocks.
Now, maybe there's some disagreement or
argument about what exactly constitutes
a full shock, how high oil prices have
to go, and how long they might need to
stay there to qualify as a shock, but
once it happens, once it gets to be
there, there is no gray area about what
what comes next. It's not inflation.
Consumers and businesses have to cut
back spending and investment and in
other ways in order to be able to pay
for more expensive energy that you just
can't do without. Energy, oil, gasoline,
diesel, they are price inelastic. You
have to buy the same amount of gas, you
have to buy the same amount of diesel,
the same amount of electricity, so if
their prices soar, the only response is
to rejigger other spending and other
costs. And for businesses as employers
who long ago stopped hiring and have
been pushed by the last couple of years
into a little bit of firing already, an
energy price shock really does risk
accelerating all the historical
negatives that come with these
circumstances. And unlike European
central bankers, European bankers like
Canadian central bankers, they seem to
be more aware of this reality. Now, part
of that is, as I said before, European
bankers were already exhibiting, to use
the ECB's phrase from its last bank
lending survey, \quote} "a high degree
of risk aversion." That was in response
to growing concerns over the private
credit bust that was last fall heading
into this year. So, we can't lose sight
of the fact that this thing is global
private credit as well as the energy
shock. It wasn't just a corporate credit
bubble here in the US, the bad
assumptions, the lack of due diligence,
and even worse, the execution, all the
garbage lending and dumb things that
American shadow bankers have done, their
European peers did, too. We've already
talked about how European insurers are
starting to walk away, and that's an
important point, too.
But once the cockroaches started showing
up, European bankers started talking
more cautiously. That was their high
degree of risk aversion. But now in the
ECB's bank lending survey follow-up,
those banks aren't just saying they're
risk averse, they're taking action on
it. Just look at the first three but the
first three bullet points from the
summary to April's bank lending survey.
\quote} "Banks tighten credit standards
across all loan categories driven by
higher perceived risk and lower risk
tolerance." "Second, banks expect to
also tighten credit standards in the
second quarter influenced by
geopolitical tensions, energy
developments, and higher funding costs.
Third, loan demand from firms and
households expected to decrease
resulting from reduced financing for
fixed investments, lower consumer
confidence, and decreased spending on
durables." Now, you've probably already
noticed how none None sounds like
inflation or would be inflationary. It
is, however, entirely consistent with
the economic data that's already coming
in, including the latest releases, which
I'll get to in just a minute. Now, the
other part of the bank lending survey
that's worth covering here is this other
bit, quote, "In a specific open-ended
question, some banks highlighted that
ongoing developments in energy prices
were driving increased liquidity demand
from firms, while others pointed to
higher uncertainty and postponement of
investments as factors dampening
demand." Now, this isn't unexpected, but
again, here we have confirmation about
what's already taking place. It's a high
degree of risk aversion on the part of
the corporate sector, as well as the
banking sector, building up a cash
cushion by drawing on either existing
credit lines with the banks or putting
in place some new ones. But, that's
going to be more difficult to do as
lending standards get tighter. So,
whenever you see this happen, it's a
critical sign telling you the situation
is getting to be very serious. And
expect to see more of this as the energy
shock continues to ripple through the
globally synchronizing system. As I said
in the introduction here, we want to
keep a close eye on Europe because
Europe is where you're going to see
those ripples, the spillover, the lack
of containment in the energy shock first
and foremost. Not only are we going to
see it, we're going to see what it looks
like.
Now, setting aside the ECB and its
biases, given instead what we just
covered from the Canadian Central Bank's
take on everything, European banks had
already had a high degree of risk
aversion and who now intend to tighten
up lending standards by the most
significant extent since the bad days of
2023,
you wouldn't expect them to do anything
other than increase their government
bond holdings and do so by a big amount.
And yes, the ECB is talking about rate
hikes and there's a very good chance
they get one or maybe even more done in
the near-term future,
but just like 2008 or 2011, banks know
what goes up will likely come right back
down. Now, again, I fully expect the
ECB, probably the Bank of Japan, and
very likely the Bank of England to do
some rate hikes. The only question is
how long before they have to reverse
course. Like I said, a fragile economy
is one that's far easier to flip into
flatter beverage territory when
confronted with an energy shock,
especially of this magnitude. But let's
not forget, you've also got a potential
credit crunch, which is what the banks
are talking about, on top of everything
else, which just makes that downside
case even more potent, as well as more
likely. So you overlook the central bank
nonsense, and you own as much safe and
liquid as you possibly can. And don't
forget, too, one reason we pay close
attention to the banking sector is the
inside information. Bankers know their
customers. They know what's going on
with them. So how the banks themselves
behave with their own assets is a huge
clue. It's not perfect. Banks obviously
can make mistakes. No one has perfect
knowledge of the future. But if you see
banks saying they have high degree of
risk aversion, and then going out and
tightening lending standards to this
degree, all the while buying the third
most government bonds during any
quarter, any really three-month period,
it's not a perfect signal, but it's one
you need to pay attention to.
Especially, especially, since it runs
contrary to the inflation narrative that
the media is running around with,
because it's been given to them by
certain central bankers, not all central
bankers, but some central bankers. So
for the first quarter of 2026, European
banks started out with the second
largest monthly increase in government
bond holdings on record. This past
January beat out last January, which is
a complete mess, 2009, all the months in
2020, and it was only behind October
2010, which was not a good comparison.
But then European banks followed up with
a smaller 15 billion increase in
February before piling on another 42
billion euros in government bonds last
month, even though oil prices were
already soaring by then. ECB hawks were
all over the place. I mean, hell, they
were even talking about a potential rate
hike here in April before they ended up
backing off somewhat, but that was only
in the past couple of weeks. European
banks, they did not care about all that
inflation noise. For the first quarter
as a whole, the total increase in their
government bond holdings was an
astonishing 152.1
billion euros. That's only behind the
first quarter of 2025, back when
everyone was expecting rate cuts out of
central banks to go along with the
financial and chaos and deflationary
pressures of the time. And here we are
with rate hike threats. And yet banks
are loading up on guvvies. The only
other three-month period with more bond
buying was in the middle of 2020.
So, the fact that banks are buying
nearly as many government bonds as they
did during those two periods is
astonishing in its own right, but even
more so when you realize during those
two periods central bank policy rates
were coming down along with market
interest rates. This time around they're
buying this many government bonds even
though they know and are very likely
assured that
ECB in particular is going to be raising
its policy rates at least in the short
run. So, what does that tell you?
European banks, they know the ECB, they
know what the ECB wants to do, they know
how much it wants to be Jean-Claude
Trichet part four,
but they're still saying, "Yeah, maybe
rates go up in the short run. However,
they're not likely to stay up because
of everything they're actually doing,
not just what they're saying. They say
they're a high degree of risk aversion,
but tightening lending standards at the
same time is pulling back.
As far as the economic data goes, it
continues to pour in. Now, I've already
talked about the services sector
sentiment from S&P Global that's PMIs
more recently. It had crashed to a
62-month low in April and that's going
to be repeated in the data that we're
going to go over here. And it makes
sense. Now oil prices becoming spiraling
inflation, you pay more for gasoline,
you've got less money available for
discretionary spending primarily on
services. So, the drop in S&P Global was
just matched by the European
Commission's data on the same thing.
Services sentiment, according to this
other survey, fell to 0.9, which may not
sound all that bad, but like SPG's
metrics, this is a 60-month low. That's
the same as where this series was in
late 2011, for example, back when Europe
was just about to fall into outright
re-recession and embarrassing
Jean-Claude Trichet yet again. In fact,
not only did Europe complete the
re-recession and deflation in 2011, it
completely exposed the rate hike
delusion. Trichet himself was actually
retired for making the same dumb mistake
about mistaking oil prices and inflation
pressures for the second time, a second
and third time. So, 0.9
is also where services sentiment had
been in July 2008, which was the first
time Trichet was hiking for oil as the
economy was melting down under his nose.
There are a lot of similarities here.
Again, the historical case, but it's not
just services. Retail sentiment in
Europe also dropped to just about minus
10, which is, it's, get this, lowest
level in 61 months, going back also to
early 2021. So, both of these sentiment
indicators point to expectations that
consumers really are going to be pulling
back, which is the same thing that's
expressed by the bank lending survey,
where banks said, as we went over
earlier, quote, "Lower consumer
confidence and decreased spending on
durables, plus a lot of decreased
spending on a whole lot more beside,
outside the view of the banking sector."
So, I don't know how many more examples
that Christine Lagarde and the rest of
the ECB needs for how this energy shock
is most likely to play out in Europe.
And as it might play out that way, it's
an early indicator for what to expect as
far as globally synchronized.
So, from the banking perspective, it's
really easy to see why those banks would
be looking through the ECB's rate hikes
in the same way the Bank of Canada is
looking through oil prices in the short
run. Is this It really is just easy
stuff. Energy shocks and fragile
economies. They are why you see lots of
recessions throughout history that's
preceded by both of those. I mean, just
Europe went through this 4 years ago.
Late 2022, fragile economy, oil spike,
outright contraction, even if it was
covered up to an extent by the lack of
immediate unemployment. But Europe, like
the rest of the world, ended up getting
it anyway, just more slowly and over
time once the economy forgot how to
grow. But from that point on, it would
only remember how to create more
joblessness and idleness in between then
and now. But now there's yet another big
energy spike. Why would it turn out to
be different this time? The only thing
which does seem to be different is how
North American central bankers are
reacting to it, Canada's first and
foremost. Not only do you have the
historic case building in the real
economy as banks are doing with their
assets, it would be the same pattern for
interest rates, which is why they're
buying so many government bonds, safety
and liquidity. So yes, a few central
banks are going to cliche themselves,
but only for a short time before history
and a high degree of risk aversion and
tighten lending standards, like gravity,
pull everything back down again,
including interest rates.
And with an energy shock comes a dollar
shock. And with a dollar shock and an
energy shock, we also get a political
shock. And there was a big one yesterday
out of the Middle East in the UAE, and I
went over that in a live video, which
the replay's linked below. As always,
thank you very much for joining me. Huge
thank you to all of you University
members and subscribers. And until next
time, take care.